Guide to the Stewart B. McKinney, District of Columbia papers, 1966-1974 MS2154
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Stewart B. McKinney, District of Columbia papers
1966-1974
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
McKinney, Stewart B.
MS2154
2 Linear Feet
Collection consists primarily of correspondence along with documents such as reports, editorials, publications, newspaper articles, and legislative documents generated or collected by Stewart B. McKinney and his office during his time as a member of the House of Representatives. This material directly relates to McKinney's work on the House District of Columbia Committee. The most prominent subject is home rule.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
In 1987 the city of Bridgeport transferred McKinney's District of Columbia files to George Washington University. It is these records that make up this collection.
Historical or Biographical Note
Stewart B. McKinney (1931-1987) served as a Republican Congressman from the state of Connecticut from 1971 until his death in 1987. During his time in Congress, McKinney served as the ranking minority member of the House District of Columbia Committee. In addition to his work on the District committee, McKinney was the second-ranking Republican on the Banking, Finance and Urban Affairs Committee. During his time in office he was a proponent of federal housing programs, home rule for the District of Columbia, and programs to help Ameriasian children and the homeless. McKinney was the author of the 1973 D.C. Home Rule Act. In addition, he was the principal author of the Urgent Relief for the Homeless Act introduced in 1987. Following his death the act was remained the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act. The McKinney Act originally consisted of fifteen programs providing a range of services to homeless people, including the Continuum of Care Programs: the Supportive Housing Program, the Shelter Plus Care Program, and the Single Room Occupancy Program, as well as the Emergency Shelter Grant Program. Though amended several times since its passage, the McKinney Act has stood the test of time, and provides the best first step to address the needs of a population that is, by and large unknown and under represented.
Before becoming active in Republican politics, he was a tire dealer in Fairfield Connecticut. McKinney was born January 30, 1931 in Pittsburgh. He attended Princeton University and earned a bachelor's degree at Yale University. He served in the Air Force from 1951-55.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consists primarily of correspondence along with documents such as reports, editorials, publications, newspaper articles, and legislative documents. All these materials were generated or collected by Stewart B. McKinney and his office during his time as a member of the House of Representatives. This material directly relates to McKinney's work on the House District of Columbia Committee. The most prominent subject is home rule. In 1973, the Home Rule Act passed in Congress, and District residents approved it in a special referendum the next year. In a historic leap for greater self-determination, District citizens elected a Mayor and Council in the fall of 1974. Voters also approved the election of Advisory Neighborhood Commissioners who represent every 2,000 residents to advise the Council on neighborhood concerns. The material dates from 1966-74.
Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; No-fault automobile insurance; Home rule; Washington (D.C.); Salaries; Legislation; McKinney, Stewart B.
- Home Rule: Agenda of Strategic Meetings, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Home Rule: - H.R. 9056 Amendments, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Home Rule: Fauntroy's Revision of the Amendment to Title VII, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Home Rule: - H.R. 9056 Bills, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Home Rule: Summary of the Bills, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Home Rule: Comments on the Provisions by DC Bar Association, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  General note
  From original folder "bill- home rule comments on the provisions by Austin F. Canfield, Jr. president of the Bar Association of D.C. 1973. Bill--Home Rule comments on the provisions by [chret?] Judge Gerard Reilly and others, 1973.
- Home Rule: House Conference Reports, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Home Rule: House Republican Conference Legislative Digest, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Home: Rule Congressional Record, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Home: Rule Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Home Rule: Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Home Rule: Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Home Rule: Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Home Rule: Inter-Congressional Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Home Rule: Non-McKinney Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Home Rule: Objections and Points of Controversy, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Home Rule: WRC TV Editorial, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Home Rule: WMAL AM FM TV Editorial, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Home Rule: WTOP Editorial, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Home Rule: DC Self-Government Fact Sheet, 10/03/1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Home Rule: Statements in House Committee Hearings, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Home Rule: Self-Determination for DC Newsletters, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Home Rule: newspaper clippings, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Home Rule: McKinney's Handwritten "Protecting the Federal Property" notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Home Rule: Commissioner's order, Mayor Walter E. Washington's order, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Home Rule: H.R. 9056 Platform of the Republican Party on DC, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Home Rule: Proposal by Metropolitan Coalition of Self-Determination for DC, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Home Rule: Nelson Commission Recommendations, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Home Rule: President Nixon's Statement of Support, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Home Rule: Survey on Home Rule by LC Congressional Reserch Service, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Home Rule: Result of the Whip Check on S. 1435 [H.R. 9056], 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Acts of 1966, 1968, 1970, 1972, 1974, 1966-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Amendments (Box 2, Folder 10)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Amendments to H.R. 4375 proxy McK--Rees Notes to Stew (Box 2, Folder 11)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Bills (Box 2, Folder 12)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Revision of Title II (Box 2, Folder 13)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Bills summary and analysers (Box 2, Folder 14)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Policemen's Association Brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Charts as supporting materials, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Comments on the Provisions, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Commissioner's order, 01/05/1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974 DC: Personnel Manual Chapter 25A, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Statement on hearings (Box 2, Folder 21)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Metro Intercom Newsletter, 01/08/1974-05/1974 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- DC Police & Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Proposal by Fire Fighters' Association for pay raise, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- DC Police and Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Publication: My Daddy is a Policeman, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- DC Police and Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: DC Police Dept. Annal. Report, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- DC Police and Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Report on Police & Firemen's Salary Act Amendment of 1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- DC Police and Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Report: Financing Alternatives for the Police and Fire Retirement System; A Report on Options Under Consideration (Box 3, Folder 4)
- DC Police and Firemen's Salary Act of 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  From original post-it on folder "House committee on DC report: Salary increases for DC Police, Firemen and Teacher Annuity increases for retired teachers real property taxes and revenue proposals
- DC Police and Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: House of Representatives Report, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- DC Police and Firemen's Salary Act of 1974: Survey of Police Pay and Benefits in Wash. Area (Box 3, Folder 7)
  From original post-it note with folder "mixture of correspondence and survey"
- DC No-Fault Motor Vehicle Insurance Act: Amendments to Committee Point of H. R. 5448, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- DC No-Fault Motor Vehicle Insurance Act: Stucky's Explanations of 9 Amendments to H.R. 5448, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- DC No-Fault Motor Vehicle Insurance Act: Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- DC No-Fault Motor Vehicle Insurance Act: Reference manual on H.R. 5448, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  From original post-it note with folder "House Subcommittee on Bureau commerce and taxation"
- Extension of DC Medical and Manpower Act of 1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Extension of DC Medical and Manpower Act of 1970: Correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Extension of DC Medical and Manpower Act of 1970: Hearings transcript, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Extension of DC Medical and Manpower Act of 1970: Report by the House Committee on DC, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Teachers' Salary Act of 1974: Bills and summary (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Teachers' Salary Act of 1974: Charts as supporting materials (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Teachers' Salary Act of 1974: Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 18)
  From original post-it note with folder "Wash Teachers' Union Barry M. Spiegel"
- Teachers' Salary Act of 1974: Hearings Statements (Box 3, Folder 19)
  From original post-it note with folder "one set is mixed with notes from Chris to Stew"
- Teachers' Salary Act of 1974: Mark-up Notice (Box 3, Folder 20)
  From original post-it note with folder "handwritten notes from Chris"
- Teachers' Salary Act of 1974: Review of the Provisions (Box 3, Folder 21)
- H. R. 5465: Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  From original post-it note with folder "Columbia Hospital Housing [conveyance of certain surplus government land to Columbia Hospital for Women]"
- H. R. 9947: Correspondence, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  From original post-it note with folder "House bill is about obscenity prosecutions"
- H. R. 11152: Correspondence, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- H. R. 11894: Correspondence, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  From original post-it note with folder "tax exempt for property owned by Nat'l Society Colonial Dames XVII Century"
- H. R. 15050: Correspondence premium tax, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  From original post-it note with folder "Amendment to "An Act to establish a code of law for DC" abolition of annuity policy premium tax.
- H. R. 15550: "Save Alexandria Waterfront", undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  From original post-it note with folder "opposition to S. 3861 and H 15550"
- DC Code to disclose police phone and address: Correpondence, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Bills House Committee on DC = Legislative Calendar, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Bills = Summary of the bills introduced by 96th Congress, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Bills = Summary of the major bills introducted and/or co-sponsored by McKinney, 1971-1978 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Miscellaneous: Correspondence on Bugging, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Auto Insurance, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Conway L. Lackman's Case, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  From original post-it note with folder: "motor operating privileges"
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Day Care Centers, DC, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Education/Reoganization Public Education in DC, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: DC Education Subcommittee, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Education/Teachers' Strike, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Education/Tuition Barry-McKinney, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: DC Emergency Housing Shelter Plan, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Fauntroy and McKinney, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Federal Funding to DC, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Health/St. Elizabeth Children's Hospital, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Hospitality House, Inc., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: House Committee on DC, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Immigration/Visa Extension, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Judge Alexander, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: McKinney's Personal Contact, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Mental Health, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Metro System, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: National Training Center for Drug Abuse Prevention, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Neighborhood Development, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Occupation Safety and Health Act Regulation Enforcement, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Preservation of DC, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Three Sisters' Bridge, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  From original post-it with folder "Federal Aid Highway Act of 1972, Report"
- DC Issues: Correspondence: Transportation, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  From original post-it with folder "Traffic Division Motorcycle Squad"
- DC Issues: General: Errata Sheets for various documents dealing with the 1970 Census (Box 4, Folder 26)
- DC Issues: General: Isabella D. DeBella Evaluation for Promotion [teacher], 1970 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- DC Issues: General: McKinney's Statement on the Metro System, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- DC Issues: General: Notice of Book Release, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- DC Issues: General: Estimated Population for DC, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- DC Issues: General: Public Service Commission, 60th Annual Report, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 31)